Finding Aid for the Carl Winning Collection of Scores, 1891-1922
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Carl Winning Collection of Scores, 1891-1922
Mus. Arc. 42
Winning, Carl, 1872-1924
2 boxes (60 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Contains 45 manuscript compositions, 4 manuscript arrangements, and 5 published compositions. It also contains an article written by Winning and two programs for concerts in Buffalo, New York.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Diane Genco, 2007.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
The following biography is quoted in full from the English translation of the entry for Winning in Buffalo und sein Deutschtum (Deutsch-Amerikanische Historische und Biographische Gesellschaft, 1911-12. The English translation by Susan Kriegbaum-Hanks, titled Buffalo and its German Community, is available online at http://www.archivaria.com/BusDbios/BusDbios18.html
Among the Germans of Buffalo Mr. Karl Georg Winning, PhD. of 17 Crescent Avenue, is celebrated as a personality of great learning especially in the philosophy of music. His reputation for profound understanding of art and strong musical aptitude precede him. Dr. Winning was born on March 15, 1872 in Frankfurt on the Oder. He was the son of the respected school director Karl Winning and his wife Rosa R., daughter of the Prussian General Music Director G. Pieske. After passing his exams at the academic high school in Frankfurt he went to the universities in Halle, Jena, and Berlin as well as the Royal Academy of Berlin to study music, the history of art, and the natural sciences. He received his doctorate in the Department of Philosophy. He fulfilled his military obligation in the Prussian Regiment of the Prince's Grenadiers No. 8 in Frankfurt on the Oder. He advanced to the rank of Reserve Officer.
In 1897 he became a correspondent for the North German Press Corps. In 1900 he became a member of the International Geographic Society in Paris, and a contributor to the journals published at Globus and Physikalische Forschungen (Physical Research). In 1893 he was musical director for the Bismarck Festival in Dresden. In 1896 he was choir master of the "Christus" performances in Bremen. From 1898 to 1900 he conducted concert and research tours through Russia, the Caucasus Mountains, and Persia. He published many compositions for orchestra, voice, piano and organ. He produced long scientific works on acoustics, tone formation, Slavic folksongs, Persian and Islamic tonality systems, audio acuteness and hearing thresholds of humans and animals, and other subjects. Most of these works are published through E. Trowitz, Bruckmann, Ries, and Erler Publishers.
In September 1907 Dr. Winning came to Buffalo to assume the baton for the Buffalo Sängerbund. He's been musical conductor ever since. The Sängerbund, Buffalo's oldest singing society, owes much of its reputation as one of the largest complex tone-producing groups in this part of the country to Dr. Winning's ability and untiring effort.
In December 1901 Dr. Winning married Miss Gussie Walldorf in Berlin. She was the youngest daughter of apothecary Dr. H. Walldorf of New York. One son, Wolfgang Karl Günther born on September 20, 1904, is the pride and joy of his parents.
According to an entry in the November 21, 1924 Buffalo Courier, Karl Winning died in Buffalo, November 19, 1924.
Scope and Content Note
Contains 45 manuscript compositions, 4 manuscript arrangements, and 5 published compositions by Carl Winning. It also contains an article written by Winning and two programs for concerts in Buffalo, New York. Three published scores of music by other composers and two manuscript scores by unidentified composers are also included. Many of the works titled in German have been left as unidentified for the time being until a more thorough examination of Winning's handwriting can be used to decipher the titles accurately. The collection has been dated according to the content related directly to Winning, not including the published scores he owned by other composers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
I. Compositions by Carl Winning
II. Arrangements by Carl Winning
III. Compositions by other composers
IV. Papers
Container List
- Compositions by Carl Winning, 1891-1922, I.; Folder 1-50
  Contains manuscript and published works
  Arranged into two subseries:
  I.A Manuscript scores by Carl Winning
  IB. Published scores by Carl Winning
  - Manuscript scores by Carl Winning, 1891-1922, I.A; Folder 1-45
    Alphabetically arranged by title.
    - Winning, Carl: 2 Ballade für Clavier, op. 79, 1916, 1 manuscript score (12 pages) (Box 1, Folder 01)
      For solo piano
      For Miss Mary Howard. The "2" in the title may indicate it is the 2nd of two ballades since there appears to only be a single work.
    - Winning, Carl: Ballet music for a New York festival, 1902 or 1903, 1 manuscript score (6 pages) (Box 1, Folder 02)
      Title transcribed from pencil note in caption.
    - Winning, Carl: Canon, undated, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf) (Box 1, Folder 03)
      Unspecified instrumentation
      Trick canon performable right side up or upside down. Remainder of title illegible.
    - Winning, Carl: Carnevalschwank für Pianoforte, op. 14, undated, 1 manuscript score (9 pages) (Box 1, Folder 04)
    - Winning, Carl: Clavierauszug zum Manfred, symphonische Dichtung, op. VII, undated, 1 manuscript score (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 05)
      Unable to establish connection between this work and Schumann or Tchaikovsky Manfred compositions.
    - Winning, Carl: Dance-Caprice, op. 89, no. 6, undated, 1 manuscript score (10 pages) (Box 1, Folder 06)
    - Winning, Carl: Drei Lieder für gemischten Chor, op. 82, 1910, 1 manuscript score (Box 1, Folder 07)
      For SATB choir
      Words in German. Includes a 2nd copy of the 3rd piece.
      Schlummerlied -- Untitled, without words --Erwacht.
    - Winning, Carl: Humoreske, op. 89, no. 3, undated, 1 manuscript score (4 pages) (Box 1, Folder 08)
    - Winning, Carl: In sonnigen Hain, 1916, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 09)
      For voice and piano
      Caption: Niagara Falls, August 1916. Words in German.
    - Winning, Carl: In vino veritas, undated, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Winning, Carl: Koenig Lear: symphonische Dichtung, Clavierauszug, 1890, 1 manuscript score (33 pages) (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Additional illegible text on title page may indicate dates of performances.
    - Winning, Carl: Malven blüte, 1916, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf) (Box 1, Folder 12)
      For voice and piano.
      Words in German.
    - Winning, Carl: Novellette, op. 89, no. 4, undated, 1 manuscript score (11 pages) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Winning, Carl: Our highest joys succeed our griefs, undated, 1 manuscript score and separate parts for treble and bass (Box 1, Folder 14)
      For 4-voice choir
      Text from Methodist Hymnal, 1905 (page 377).
    - Winning, Carl: Rätselcanon, 1922, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Winning, Carl: Scherzo, op. 89, no. 5, undated, 1 manuscript score (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Winning, Carl: Scherzo und Finale: 2 Clavierstücke für Pianoforte, op. 17, undated, 1 manuscript score (5 pages) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Winning, Carl: Scherzo no. 2, 1893?, 1 manuscript score (13 pages) (Box 1, Folder 18)
      "Dresden" -- title page.
    - Winning, Carl: Schlaf mein Jesulein, 1914?, 1 manuscript score and 6 parts (Box 1, Folder 19)
      For solo voice, two sopranos, and alto
    - Winning, Carl: Sehnsucht? Eifersucht?, 1916, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Winning, Carl: Solstice (Sonnenwende): First American suite for piano, op. 86. No. 1: Prelude alla toccata, undated, 1 manuscript score (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Winning, Carl: Solstice (Sonnenwende): First American suite for piano, op. 86. No. 2: Impromptu, undated, 1 manuscript score (6 pages) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Winning, Carl: Solstice (Sonnenwende): First American suite for piano, op. 86. No. 3: Notturno, undated, 1 manuscript score (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Winning, Carl: Solstice (Sonnenwende): First American suite for piano, op. 86. No. 4: Caprice, undated, 1 manuscript score (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes first 2 pages of a second copy.
    - Winning, Carl: Solstice (Sonnenwende): First American suite for piano, op. 86. No. 5: Intermezzo, undated, 1 manuscript score (4 pages) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Winning, Carl: Solstice (Sonnenwende): First American suite for piano, op. 86. No. 6: Soaring, undated, 1 manuscript score (11 pages) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Winning, Carl: Spinn! Spinn!, undated, 1 manuscript score (3 pages) (Box 1, Folder 27)
      For 4-part vocal ensemble
    - Winning, Carl: Tatenfest, 1914, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 28)
      For 2 sopranos
      Words in German. First line of text: Was macht irh lass.
    - Winning, Carl: Thema zur Tarandelle (incomplete), undated, 1 manuscript score (12 pages) (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Chiefly sketches, includes a portion with heading Allegro molto agitato.
    - Winning, Carl: Valsette, undated, 1 manuscript score (4 pages) (Box 1, Folder 30)
      For violin and piano
    - Winning, Carl: Weihnacht: soprano solo, 1914, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf) (Box 1, Folder 31)
      For solo soprano
    - Winning, Carl: Wir weiss wie das wird, 1914, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified piano composition, C minor, undated, 1 manuscript score (7 pages) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified piano composition, D major, undated, 1 manuscript score (3 pages) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified piano composition: In …, undated, 1 manuscript score (2 parts: 12 and 17 pages) (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Title illegible, begins with "In". Two scores grouped together based on recognizably common thematic material.
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified piano composition, no. 2-3, undated, 1 manuscript score (4 pages) (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Work captioned No. 3 is incomplete.
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified piano composition, 1891, 1 manuscript score (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Pencil inscription at end of score: Berlin 1891.
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified piano and violin composition, 1913, 1 manuscript score (3 pages) (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Caption title illegible.
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified song in German, op. 10, no. 2, undated, 1 manuscript score (3 pages) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified song in German, op. 12, no. 2, undated, 1 manuscript score (6 pages) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified song in German, L…, 1891, 1 manuscript score (4 pages) (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Caption title illegible but may begin with "L". Incomplete.
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified song in German, 1895, 1 manuscript score (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified song in German, Z…, undated, 1 manuscript score (21 pages) (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Caption title illegible but may begin with "Z".
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified sketches, undated, 1 folder (circa 31 manuscript leaves) (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Chiefly unspecified instrumentation
    - Winning, Carl: Unidentified sketches grouped by letter designations, undated, 1 folder (10 groupings of manuscript leaves) (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Chiefly unspecified instrumentation.
      Grouped by Winnings markings of lettering.
  - Published scores by Carl Winning, circa 1894-1898, I.B; Folder 46-50
    Four scores published by Verlag von Ries und Erler, Berlin.
    - Winning, Carl: Drei Lieder für eine Singstimme mit Clavierbegleitung, op. 15, circa 1898, 1 score (9 pages) (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Verlag von Ries und Erler
      Wie der Mond kam es gegangen (H. Seidel) -- Unterm Machandelbaum (E. v. Wildenbruch) -- Liebeslied (Schnadahüpfl).
    - Winning, Carl: Intermezzi, op. 14, no. 3-6, circa 1897, 1 score (11 pages) (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Heft II.
    - Winning, Carl: Sonnenstäubchen: 8 Lieder aus dem Serre von Feisi für eine Singstimme mit Klavierbegleitung, op. 4, circa 1895, 1 score (11 pages) (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Dem Seelenkranken -- Der Sonne -- Meiner Seele -- Dem Ewigen -- Mir -- Dem All -- Den Pilgern -- Dem Licht.
    - Winning, Carl: Valse brillante pour piano, op. 5, circa 1894, 1 score (13 pages) (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Name stated as Charles Winning on cover, Carl Winning in caption.
- Arrangements by Carl Winning, 1911-1912, II.; Folder 51-54
  Contains manuscript arrangements of works by other composers.
  Alphabetically arranged by composer surname.
  - Brahms, Johannes: Lieder, op. 49. Wiegenlied, arranged, 1911, 1 manuscript score (2 pages); Arranged by Carl Winning. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    For 4-voice men's choir
  - Gabriel, Charles Hutchinson: Only a contrite sinner, undated, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf); Arranged by Carl Winning. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    For 4-voice choir.
    Words in English by Ida Reed.
  - Grieg, Edvard: Peer Gynt. Morgenstemning, arranged, undated, 1 manuscript score (4 pages); Arranged by Carl Winning. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    For organ
    Lacking title.
    Followed by a setting of Bach's Ein feste Burg ist unser Gott (2 pages)
  - Weber, Carl Maria: Webers op. 65 mit canonsichen Veranderungen für 2 Claviere, 1912, 2 manuscript parts (24, 14 pages); Arranged by Carl Winning. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    For 2 pianos
    Arrangement of Weber's Aufforderung zum Tanze.
- Compositions by other composers, 1837-1905, III.; Folder 55-58
  Contains scores by other composers.
  - Mason, William: System of fundamental technic for modern piano playing, 1905, 1 score (189 pages); Edited by W.S.B. Mathews. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Oliver Ditson Company.
  - Bound volume containing piano etudes by Kessler, Kreutzer, Czerny, and Rubinstein, 1837-1887, 1 volume containing five works (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Some works marked with performance/study markings.
    20 ausgewählte Etuden für Pianoforte op. 100 Heft II / Joseph Christoph Kessler (Julius Engelmann, 1887) -- Die Schule des Fugenspiels und des Vortrags mehrstimiger Sätze und deren besonderer Schwierigkeiten (Diabelli, circa 1837); Schule des Virtuosen, op. 365 (C.F. Peters, 1887) / Czerny -- 20 ausgewählte Etuden für Pianoforte op. 100 Heft I / Joseph Christoph Kessler (Julius Engelmann, 1887) -- 6 Etudes pour le piano, op. 23 / Anton Rubinstein (C.F. Peters, circa 1880).
  - Rudorff, Ernst: Sechs vierhändige Clavier-Stücke, op. 4, circa 1865, 1 score (pages 5-33) (Box 2, Folder 57)
    For piano, 4 hands
    Includes markings. Caption of page 5: "Carl Winning, op. 18 no. 2, 1892".
    Breitkopf und Härtel
    Lacking cover, title page, and pages 1-4. Identified as Rudorff's work through comparison.
  - Unidentified composers: Fallen star; I'm getting older, undated, 2 manuscript scores (Box 2, Folder 58)
    On verso of I'm getting older: I'm living in hopes / words and music by Victor Marcy.
- Papers, 1900-1922, IV.; Folder 59-60
  Contains concert programs and an article by Winning.
  - Winning, Carl: Bilder aus Russland, 1900, 1 bound volume; In German. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Contains Winning's serially published article as clipped from a journal and pasted onto pages.
  - Concert programs, 1912, 1922, 2 programs (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Sunday April 14 1912: 139th free organ concert at the City Convention Hall, Buffalo, N.Y. given by Dr. Carl Winning -- April 20 1922 Schwaebischer Saengerbund, Dr. Carl Winning, Director. Zweites Saison Konzert, Elmwood Music Halle.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Music--Manuscripts; Winning, Carl, 1872-1924--Archives
Genres
Scores
Associated Material
Separated Material
Some standard editions of piano literture received with the collection were discarded due to very poor condition.